[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
I wanted to do a little more with the
idea of a particle in an electromagnetic
field I wanted to work out in more
detail the theory of a particle in an
electromagnetic field a Charged particle
we're not going to worry in this course
about the Dynamics of the field itself
of course the Dynamics of the field
itself the field is a dynamical
system it itself has equations of motion
you going follow them for our purposes
now the electric and magnetic fields are
simply given to us and in fact to make
things simple let's suppose that the
electric and magnetic fields don't
depend on time although they may depend
on space
I've worked out for you the theory of a
Charged particle moving in a um in a
magnetic field I thought we would redo
that talk about it a little bit because
it is it is unintuitive some things
about it are
unintuitive in particular the canonical
formulation of it the hamiltonian
formulation the notion of
momenta is a little bit
surprising and there are some
unintuitive things about the way a
particle moves in a magnetic field uh in
particular when you add an electric
field so it's called the hall effect for
those who Wonder uh who may know what
I'm talking
about all right so let's uh
begin we have various in fact we have
various different formulations of
mechanics that we've done up till now
let's just list list
them list the various forms we're going
to learn one new form but the first form
is just equations of motion f equals ma
right uh let's call it
equations of
motion and those are typically
differential equations which come down
from above Newton or somebody tells us
what those equations of motion are and
they're of the form of second order
differential equations for the
coordinates of a system
next was the principle of least
action not any equation that we can
write down will be of the form that it
can be derived from a principle of least
action
but all the fundamental equations of
physics are derivable from principle of
least action including incidentally the
field equations governing the
electromagnetic field but we haven't
gotten to that yet
least action from the principle of least
action we can derive another form namely
the lrange equations of motion lran form
those are derived by applying the method
of the calculus of variations to the
principle of least action in other words
the oiler lrange equations and that
gives us the lran form
and then finally by concentrating on
phase space the P's and the q's we
ultimately wound up with a hamiltonian
form they each have their advantages and
disadvantages the hamiltonian form is
perhaps the least intuitive on the other
hand it has the most to do first of all
with quantum mechanics but second of all
with information
flow it has this lovely picture of a
flow of points through phase space which
if you follow them you not only see how
a single system behaves you see how the
whole ensemble of systems with different
initial conditions will behave and
allows you to compare them it allows you
to discuss for example information
conservation and other things that will
come through so that's the advantage of
the hamiltonian form
the disadvantage is in some ways it's
less intuitive in particular we'll see
that tonight when we talk about the
electromagnetic
particle lran form very very general
very very
powerful uh I can't think of very many
disadvantages of it it's uh powerful
except that it doesn't do some of the
nice things that the hamiltonian form
does namely allow you to plot a flow
through the phas base the principle of
least action that underlies everything
extremely deep but in its form in the
form in which you write it down it is
not terribly useful the way you use it
is to derive equations of motion from it
namely go to the L grangian form so the
principle of least action underlies the
whole
shebang but by
itself uh it doesn't tell you how to
solve problems so
easily minimize the action usually you
do that by solving a differential
equation and equations of motion well
those of course are the uh lowest common
denominator in the sense that all
systems have equations of motion we
learn about them in elementary physics
fals
ma um but just knowing that there are
equations of motion differential
equations is not sufficient to tell you
about energy momentum and all the
special things things that go with the
special form of the equations that
physics makes use of so they're all
interesting and all
useful um we can
apply each of these to the motion of a
particle in an electromagnetic field now
for tonight I'm mostly going to be
interested in a particle moving in an
electromagnetic field in two
Dimensions uh just because it's easy to
visualize in other words a particle free
to move around on the black board in an
electromagnetic field where for
Simplicity the magnetic field will be
into the board no components along the
surface of the board and the electric
field will be parallel to the board
we'll come to that but before we do let
me write down the general equation of
motion for a non-relativistic particle
for a non relativistic particle this one
this means one moving slowly by
comparison with the speed of light
uh and it's just FAL ma
force is equal to mass time acceleration
but now I have to tell you what the
force is the force is given in terms of
the
um first of all the charge of the
particle called
Q then there's a term proportional to
the electric field the electric field is
a vector
that makes sense acceleration is a
vector and magnetic term which is
velocity
dependent depends on the velocity again
it's proportional to the electric
charge it contains the velocity
Vector cross the magnetic
field uh depending on your choice of
units some familiar units put a c down
here where C is the speed of light I'm
going to leave it
out uh you will find in some choices of
units in fact in a lot of choices of
units the speed of light is included
down here but this uh doesn't matter you
can either absorb the speed of light
into a new definition of the charge or a
new definition of the magnetic field or
you can remember
that it's always V divided by the speed
of light when I write V you can think to
yourself he really means V divided by
the speed of light either
way the
main um structure of the equation is
mass time acceleration is equal to an
electric field
term plus a magnetic field term the
magnetic field term has the property
that the force depends on the velocity
but but unlike a friction Force the
force is perpendicular to the velocity
cross products are perpendicular to the
constituent vectors which make them up
so uh and in fact what that means is
that if a particle is moving the
magnetic force does not accelerate it
along the trajectory it accelerates it
perpendicular to the
trajectory and for that reason it
doesn't change the speed of the particle
not changing the speed of the particle
means that it doesn't change the kinetic
energy magnetic fields do no work that's
the uh that's the catch uh
phrase all right so this is one form
um as I said I will mainly be interested
in magnetic fields or or Motion in the
plane in the plane of a Blackboard the
white board where the magnetic field is
perpendicular to the plane the velocity
of course is in the plane so the
velocity is in the plane the magnetic
field is
perpendicular the cross product of V
crossb is also in the plane it's
perpendicular to B if B is perpendicular
to the plane the force lies in the plane
so the whole motion takes place in the
plane or can be constrained to take
place in the plane and if the electric
field
also lies in the plane that just gives
another contribution to the acceleration
in the plane
itself all right so this is uh this is
our setup now let's go to the principle
of least action oh let me write down one
other equation which doesn't come in in
any useful way into into the equation of
motion in this form but it is necessary
to go either to to make the step from
equation of motion to any of these other
formulations you need another idea you
need the idea of the vector
potential all
right the vector potential the vector
potential is just defined by saying the
magnetic
field is
equal to the
curl of some Vector that's called the
vector
potential now there's something
special about vectors which are curls of
other vectors anybody know what it
is they have zero
Divergence we talked about what a
Divergence is but basically it's the
spread of the vector field away from a
point anything which is a curl has zero
Divergence the magnetic field has zero
Divergence what about an electric field
do electric field have zero
Divergence what's if we write the
Divergence of the electric field del. e
what's on the right hand
side the charge density the charge
density what is it telling us that D.B
is equal to
zero yes it's telling us that there's no
analog in
nature of electric charge
which creates sources of the magnetic
field no point magnetic
sources which create magnetic
field now is it true that there really
are no magnetic
monopoles probably
not but nobody's ever discovered one so
until somebody discovers one we can at
least assume that for the purpose of the
physics uh that we normally do that
there are no magnetic charges and the
curl of the maget the um the Divergence
of the magnetic field is zero any field
whose Divergence is zero can always be
expressed as the curl of something else
but not in a unique
way not in a unique way we'll come back
to that non-uniqueness there's a
non-uniqueness in the vector potential
here that the vector potential can be
changed without changing the magnetic
field the equations of motion only
depend on the magnetic field we could
write that the magnetic field is the
curl of the vector
potential but the equations are such
that changing the vector potential
keeping the magnetic field the same
doesn't change the motion of the
particle that's called gauge invariance
we will come back to gaug in variance in
fact we'll probably come back to it
tonight but for the moment just keep
keep in mind that this construction of a
vector
potential is
ambiguous I'll give you some examples as
we go along what about the electric
field how do we usually represent the
electric field is just a more ordinary
non velocity dependent Force it's very
much like the ordinary forces that we've
studied up till now it doesn't depend on
velocity it does depend on position
it's also
conservative conservative means that it
respects the conservation of energy and
what do we know about conservative
forces we know that they're generated
from potential energy functions from
potential energy functions
force is equal to
minus the gradient of a potential energy
function to write it in terms of
components it's the equation that we've
written the I component of the force is
minus the derivative with respect to
XI of a potential energy
function
now in electricity and
magnetism it's normal oh all right first
of all the electric force has this uh
this particular
behavior and to to ensure it what one
writes is that the electric
field is equal to minus the
gradient of a quantity called v v is
essentially the potential energy but not
quite what's it missing well we have
mass time acceleration is equal to
charge time e so e is not quite Force
charge time e is force and therefore
potential energy is charge times
V that's all the uh the V what does v
stand
for volts it's measured in volts and a
volt is an energy per unit charge is
what it is that's all a volt is it's an
energy per unit
charge and um this is a convention to
some
extent that we instead of writing U we
write V but then multip ly it by Q to
find the potential energy of a charge
but it also tells us that all things
being equal the force and the potential
energy on a charge is proportional to
the charge double the charge you double
the potential energy and so
forth okay so we could rewrite this
these equations here in terms of
the potential
V sometimes just call the electric
potential
and the vector potential a by just
plugging in to here and
here let's come next to the principle of
least
action the only known formula for an
action which gives rise to this equation
requires you to use the vector potential
you can't get away with it nobody knows
and in fact you can prove that you can't
write a principle of least action which
de directly with the magnetic field you
have to use the vector potential well
that's a little bit odd because at the
end of the
day the
um the behavior of a particle doesn't
depend on the vector potential it
depends on the magnetic field you can
change the vector potential without
changing the magnetic field and the
motion of the particle doesn't depend on
the uh on the vector potential but
nevertheless to write the principle of
least ACC ction you must introduce the
vector potential here it
is the action for particle is an as
always is an
integral it has the usual 1 12 mv^ s the
kinetic
energy 12
M
uh let's write it out explicitly x do^ 2
+ y do 2 I'm leaving out the Z component
of the motion because I'm as I said
let's concentrate on two Dimensions if
we wanted to put the third dimension in
we
would MX do s or just mv^
s it then has the good
old uh potential energy which would just
be minus
U for an ordinary potential energy we
would write minus U of X and Y now we
write minus charge * V of X and Y
and we integrate this
DT what else would we integrate it with
DT but then that does not capture the
physics of the magnetic field we have to
add plus the integral again the
charge the vector
potential let's write it in components
first a subi DX sub
I we take the path and we break it up
into little infinitesimal
segments each segment is a DX and a
Dy we call the combination DX and Dy we
call it DX sub
I and we take the component of the
vector potential multiply it by the
corresponding component of
DX and integrated we don't need any DT
in here we have a DX so that's just
along the trajectory in each little
interval there we take we can call it
dx. a if we think of DX as a little
vector and a is a vector then what
appears here is a.
DX okay so this is also a line an
integral along the trajectory from the
beginning I won't bother putting in the
boundaries the end points of the
integration it's from the beginning of
the trajectory to the end of the
trajectory and that is the action for a
particle in an electromagnetic
field now let me uh take just to um to
show you some of the symmetry of this
formula let me take this term and put it
over here and write it as minus
q v
DT let's remove it from
here this is kind of interesting Q comes
out Q goes along with all of the
terms what do we have here we have for
each each direction of space we have an
A subi * a DX subi and then for the time
component we have a v * DT it's as if if
we plotted the motion in space time now
we are not talking about relativity for
the moment but you can see that what's
being set up
here is going to be particular
particularly simple when we think about
the special theory of relativity where x
and t form SpaceTime but let's put in t
here X and Y and imagine a trajectory we
now break up the trajectory into little
bits and now what we have from the
electromagnetic field is a term as subi
dxi minus vdt it's almost as if not
almost as if it is as if
the was the fourth
component of a vector
potential and that this is a combination
that involves all four directions of
space Oh sorry all four directions of
space and time dotted into a
three-dimensional Vector potential and
its fourth component now if you're not
familiar with special relativity don't
worry about it right now this is the
form that the action takes
this adx looks a little bit unfamiliar
up till now our action has involved the
integral of a lran and a lran is a
function of velocities and
positions a is a function of position a
is a vector field in
space it depends on position all three
components of it depend on position V
also depends on position in general
a could also depend on time and so could
V but it does not depend on the
velocities so this is something which
depends on
position but it has this odd form of
being multiplied by DX of I well to get
it to look more ordinary just divide by
DT and multiply by
DT we can also divide by DT over
here and now we see
that the lran for the particle in the
electromagnetic field has the usual
form uh yeah we could write this
VI here no V is a
scalar a oh yes oh yes a. DX is a
sum no that's right but uh we're calling
two yeah we're going to wind up calling
as usual two things by the same symbol
is velocity and there's potential I'll
try to use if I ever here here it is
right here let's be careful let's call a
small
V small V for velocity
a sub I DX by D DX by
DT can also be written as the DOT
product of the vector potential with the
velocity all right so let's do that
let's just call this uh a
A.V sorry a do small V and these are
both
vectors so that's our lran this is our
principle of least
action the true root trajectory
minimizes the
action and it immediately tells us what
the lran is to get the lran all we have
to do is
erase the integration
signs and lran is plus
Q times
A.V a. Little V
minus V of
X this is now on the wrong line it
should be next to L Gran
here we can go through the construction
of the hamiltonian I won't do that
now it's a standard
construction
um let's leave that for either later
maybe we won't even need it very much Al
together but let's concentrate now on
the gauge inv
variance what kind of things can you do
to the vector potential that don't
change the magnetic field and therefore
do not change the physics remember the
real basic differential equations here
do not involve the vector potential that
means there some sort of redundancy of
the
description because we can change the
vector potential without changing the uh
the physics and we can also think of it
as a kind of symmetry a kind kind of
symmetry of the
system where changing the vector
potential in a certain way has no
influence on the motion it's kind of
symmetry it's called gaug
invariance and here's the way it
works let's take as a let's just to uh
to understand it let's focus on a
particular component of Del cross a
let's say the Z
component but all the other components
work the same way what is the Z
component of Del cross a it is
derivative with respect to X that means
d by DX of a
y minus the derivative with respect to Y
of ax that's its
definition right now supposing I add
I'll write it in uh in uh in Vector
notation and then just explicitly in
components supposed I add to the vector
potential something which is itself a
gradient to call it Lambda Lambda of X
what is a gradient a gradient simply
means the I component we add to the I
component of a we add derivative with
respect to x
i of Lambda now Lambda can be anything
the point is that changing a in this way
doesn't change the curl of a let's see
why that is supposing I now recalculate
the curl of a after having introduced
this extra term
here for example let's take the X and Y
component a
subx will now have the new term d by DX
of Lambda and a suby will now have the
new term d by
Dy of
Lambda Lambda of X means Lambda of X and
Y in
general X and
Y let's just leave it that way okay what
happens to the curl the curl gets
another piece it gets
plus derivative with respect to X of the
new term in a y the new term in a y is d
by Dy of Lambda
but then we have to correct this term
that's
minus d by Dy of the new term in ax the
new term in ax is derivative with
respect to X of
Lambda well these are exactly the same
thing d by DX d by Dy of Lambda is
exactly the same thing as d by Dy d by
DX the order of operations of
derivatives is immaterial
and so by adding the gradient of a
scaler to a vector it does not change
its curl another way to say it is the
gradient of a scaler doesn't have a curl
is curl
free
so by adding to the vector potential the
gradient of a scaler we change the
vector potential we change L grangian
but we don't change the equation of
motion I will remind you it's somewhere
in your notes I worked out uh well maybe
we should do it let's do it over again
let's uh just to keep the lecture
self-contained let's work out the
equation of
motion and starting with the lran and
see that it really does have uh the form
incidentally this equation up here has a
name the right hand side is the lorence
force
law lorence l o r n TZ the same
gentleman who first wrote down the Len
Transformations okay
so this term is called the Loren Force
law let's check that this lran gives
rise to Loren's equation of motion for
the motion of a particle we just do the
usual thing let's just do the X
component well just do the X component
let's not bother with the Y component we
start with the X component and we first
calculate the canonical momentum
conjugate to X that's the derivative of
the lran with respect to x
dot so p
subx p subx is equal to the derivative
of L grangian with respect to x dot
that's MX dot that's not surprising
that's just
MV grow momentum but then there's
another
term
the x dot also appears in A.V this is x
dot time a subx so there's another term
q a subx and that's it Q * a
subx so we see something
odd that the canonical moment
momentum is equal to the thing we
usually call Momentum MV plus an extra
term which depends on the vector
potential but this is strange because
the extra term is itself not gaug in
variant it depends on the vector
potential if I change the vector
potential by adding something to it I
will change the momentum well that's
okay we follow the mathematics if the
mathematics tells us to do it we do it
the canonical momentum of a point
particle in a magnetic field is not
gauge
invariant it means it's not a thing you
really measure it depends on your choice
of the vector we're going to give some
examples of different choices of vector
potentials and see how the whole thing
works but this is the canonical momentum
now what's the equation of motion the
equation of motion is that the time
derivative of this the derivative of PX
with respect to
T is equal to the derivative
now this is just lr's equations d by DL
let's write it
down derivative of L grangian with
respect to x dot d by
DT that's just derivative of p is equal
to partial of L with respect to
X well the left hand side is just the
time derivative of this so we can write
MX Dot
that's the first term of d by DT dld DX
Dot and then the second term is plus
Q times the time derivative of a subx I
told you that a subx was not a function
of time does that mean that it doesn't
depend on time no what it means is it
doesn't depend explicitly on time here's
a point you may have a field in space
which varies in space but does not vary
in time
all right it doesn't vary in time at all
it's just something some spatially
dependent thing but if a particle moves
through it then by virtue of the motion
of the particle from point to point the
field at the particle does change with
time right and to work out the change in
time we just write that this is equal to
the derivative of a subx with respect to
x times the time derivative of
X Plus
the derivative of a
subx with respect to Y times the time
derivative of
y all right a at the position a subx at
the position of the particle changes
because the particle is moving and
here's the time derivative of
a that's the left side what about the
right
side
equals um now what he
depends on X let's write this out this
is a
q a subx * x dot plus a suby * y dot
minus V of X and
Y oh there should be a q
here yeah
Q all right what depends on X ax depends
on X in general a y depends on x
and V depends on
X the X dots don't depend on X just ax
and a y and V depend on X so on the
right hand side let's write down what we
get we get
Q times the derivative of a
subx with respect to
X time x
dot what I'm writing is partial of L
with respect respect to X so we get one
term by differentiating a subx over here
with respect to X another term from
differentiating a sub y with respect to
X that's plus
Q derivative of a suby with respect to
x times what
times
uh time y
dot that's the derivative of this term
with respect to X and then we get
minus
Q DV by
DX first of all Q DV by DX what is that
that's Q * the electric field so that's
this term in Loren's Force
law we can forget about it for
now that's in good
shape on the left hand side we have some
terms Each of which involves the
derivative of a with respect to x times
some sort of x dot on the right hand
side we have similar things perhaps some
of them cancel let's see what
cancels both the left and the right we
have the ax subx with respect to x x x
dot here and
here so the whole right hand side then
what do we have here
um
sorry we can now transpose this term
over here to the right hand side and
let's see what we have we have first of
all from here
Q then the
AY by
DX time y
Dot and and then from here we have minus
D
ax by
Dy * y
dot d a y by DX minus D ax by Dy what is
that that's B
subz so this is
Q * B
subz * y Dot
that's exactly this term here it has a
velocity it has a magnetic
field and if we're interested in the X
component of V
crossb then it has
bz and Y component of velocity so that's
this so indeed we do reproduce the Loren
equation of motion but even more than
that we see that the vector potential
only appears in the form of the magnetic
field despite the fact that we had to
use it to write down the L grangian the
vector potential appears in a gauge
invariant way another
words what appears here the B field does
not change when you make a gauge
transformation so that's that's one of
The
Oddities of physics uh that it requires
you quite often to introduce some
redundant descriptions of things it's
not that you have to introduce a
redundant description of things you
could have worked just with
this but in order to make the equations
look like principle of least action
orians hamiltonians and so forth there
are times when you have to introduce
redundant descriptions of things and
those redundant descriptions are called
gaug
invariances the Transformations which
correspond to these redundancies the
changes that you make that are really no
changes at all in the underlying physics
those are typically called gauge
Transformations so whenever you hear
about gauge and variance one is always
talking about some kind of redundancy
that's necessary to work out the
canonical formulation of a theory but
where the redundancy doesn't enter into
the actual motion of a
system okay so there we we are we have
uh the
lanan have we have this now I want to
give you some explicit examples of
vector Potentials in particular I want
to concentrate on the problem of a
uniform magnetic field one which doesn't
vary from place to
place that's the simplest situation
magnetic field pointing into the
Blackboard which has no variation just a
uniform constant magnetic field how do
we construct one from a vector potential
we want bz to be independent of position
so
bz is equal to derivative with respect
to X of a
y plus minus derivative with respect to
Y of
ax I'll give you two examples of vector
potentials which do the job we want bz
to be a constant let's say a constant
let's take B let's assume that b is in
into the Blackboard in other words it is
positive and it's and its magnitude I'll
just call little B the magnitude of the
magnetic field all right then we can
take a sub here's an example take a y
equal to the number B time x and ax =
Z in that case the derivative with
respect to X of a y is just B
the X goes away when we take the
derivative on the other hand ax is equal
to zero and this doesn't change the
answer so this is one
possible choice of vector potential
which will give rise to the uniform
magnetic field here's another
one a y equal
Z and ax anybody want to guess
minus B *
y just just check it this time d x of a
y is equal to zero but d y by of Da ax
is equal to minus B and gives you the
same answer here I'll give you another
example it has to be minus because
there's a minus here yeah if we want to
get if we want to get the same answer
yeah here's another
example all giving the same magnetic
field a y = b/
2x ax = minus b over2 y also will give
the same
answer these different Vector potentials
are related by gauge Transformations
it's not too hard to work out that
there's some scaler I won't write it
down there's some
scaler uh that takes you from one to the
other by taking uh by taking its uh
gradient right so these are three
different and there's an infinite number
of other ones an infinite number of
other um formulations for the vector
potential which give exactly the same uh
magnetic field one can use any one of
them it doesn't matter since the net
final equations of motion don't depend
on the vector potential they only depend
on the magnetic field let's take these
two examples let's forget this one
here and concentrate
on these two
um let's let me rewrite
it ax = b y
a y equal
Z or and the other possibility is a y
equal 0 a x is equal to no uh a x is
equal to
zero a y is equal to minus B *
X in the lingo these would be two
different
gauges two different gauges giving rise
to the same uh to the same field okay
let's see what we learn by from
conservation laws let's start with this
gauge over here okay let's forget the
second gauge let's start with a gauge in
which ax is equal to b y and a y is
equal to
zero uh let me rewrite the lran in
detail
now and I'll tell you what for
Simplicity for the moment let's forget
the electric field we'll come back to
the influence of the electric field in a
little while
okay so a * V means now ax * x
dot I've set a y equal to zero in this
first choice of
gaug okay and furthermore ax is equal to
B *
y so that's my lran and now let's
calculate the canonic momenta conjugate
to X and to Y let's start with
PX PX is the derivative of L grangian
with respect to x dot that's MX
dot plus
QB
Y is this conserved or isn't it
conserved well let's write down the
other one
py is equal to myy
dot plus
nothing which one do you think if any
are
conserved all right we'll take a vote is
this
conserved is this
conserved any of them conserved yes no
good yeah okay but still are any of them
conserved that's that's one possible
answer anybody say
yes oh come on I want to embarrass
you
okay this one is conserved why is it
conserved this is the X component of
momentum and notice the L grangian
doesn't depend on X it depends on x dot
but x dot is not X and it depends on y
if I make a transformation X goes to x +
Epsilon
the X component of the Velocity doesn't
change I've just translated the system a
little bit in the X direction that
doesn't change x dot it doesn't change y
dot doesn't change x dot over here and
it doesn't change
why why because I haven't changed y
That's
why that means that the X component the
momentum is conserved there's a symmetry
X goes to X plus a constant what about y
goes to Y plus a
constant this term changes if y goes to
if you shift y a little bit this term
changes so the Y component of momentum
is not
conserved all right let's forget it
since it's not
conserved for the moment what we've
learned is that in this
gauge this quantity is conserved D well
I don't need to say in this gauge I can
just say MX
do plus
QB Y is conserved for example if it
starts out being zero let's take that
case suppose it starts out being zero
then it will stay equal to zero let's
take that case for
Simplicity if it starts out zero it
stays zero if it's not zero it'll stay
whatever it is
okay and we'll understand in a little
while what that
means okay that tells me that
immediately solves for me and tells me
that x dot the X component of velocity
is minus q b over
M time
y That's what I learned from
conservation laws it's very odd first of
all it's odd because the X component the
momentum is not what you might have
thought namely just X do MX Dot and
second of all in the particular gauge
that we're
writing since there's an X translation
in variance we can immediately conclude
that the X component the momentum is
conserved and that tells us if it starts
zero it stays zero later on we'll worry
about what if it's not
zero okay now let's go to the other
gauge
oh and incidentally this equation
here that x dot this doesn't have
anything to do this is completely gaug
invariant it just tells us that the
velocity the X component of velocity is
proportional to y let's find out another
piece of information by working out the
theory in the other gauge in the other
gauge the lran becomes
minus
QB x * y
dot the Y component of momentum which is
now the one I'm going to be interested
in py is myy
dot
minus
qbx in this gauge py is conserved oops
sorry
y dot
yeah in this gauge py is conserved why
because the LAN doesn't depend on y
seems to me I said that before do I have
a lran doesn't depend on y so py is
conserved okay a shift of Y doesn't
change lran in this gauge a shift of X
changes the lran but a shift in y
doesn't change the lran and so
this quantity here is also conserved in
the motion of a Charged particle for
example if it starts zero it will stay
zero in which case y dot is equal to
this time it's
plus QB over M *
X I haven't had to solve any equations
all I did was write down the
conservation laws and I found out that
the X component of velocity is
proportional to minus y and the Y
component of velocity is proportional to
X that should ring a bell to some of you
maybe not to all but we'll work it out
I'll ring your bell for
you um what kind of motion is
this that's circular motion so let's
prove that it's circular
motion
and see what we can find out about the
circular motion
let's consider a particle moving in a
circle about the origin for
Simplicity what is uh what is the what
is its equation well let's call this
angle Theta let's call its distance from
the origin
R then
X is equal to R * cosine of theta but if
we're going to allow Theta to evolve and
swing around here with an angular
velocity Omega we can write that
this is equal to R
cosine of Omega T and Y is equal to R
sin Omega
T this is uniform motion with an angular
velocity Omega number of radians per
second is Omega let's check that this
solves this equation here so what is x
dot x
dot is just differentiating this with
respect to time that's equal to R
Omega and then the derivative of cosine
is minus s minus sin Omega
T and Y dot is equal to R Omega cosine
Omega
t x dot is supposed to be minus
something * y x do is minus something *
Y and Y dot is supposed to be that same
something time
X Y dot is that same something time
x in order to find out what Omega is we
just have to match these equations so
here we have x dot is equal to - QB / M
* y here we have that x dot is - Omega *
y x dot is minus Omega * y the RS cancel
out all right so I can write just from
this here that x dot is equal to minus
Omega time Y and also a similar equation
for y dot well if I compare that with
this equation here I immediately find
that Omega the angular frequency it's
called a cyclotron frequency is equal to
minus
QB over
M yes and it's Omega what am I writing Q
Omega Omega is q b/ m the charge of the
particle divided by its
mass notice that combination ratio of
charge to mass times the magnitude of
the magnetic field that's the angular
frequency the larger the charge the
larger the angular frequency the larger
the mass the slower the angular
frequency this combination Q over M was
what made it hard uh at about the turn
of the 20th century to determine the
charge and mass of the electron because
it always comes into most things in the
ratio Q over M and so measurements of
the trajectory of electrons and so forth
in magnetic fields yield the ratio of Q
to M but it doesn't give q and M
separately something else had to be done
to do
that okay
um now this may the whole thing May
strike you as
odd that we have this redundancy of
description we can shift the vector
potential change the whole formalism but
nevertheless extract out interesting and
useful information from the conservation
laws in fact I used two different gauges
to get two different pieces of uh of uh
conservation laws
um what happens if I did not send if I
did not require
PX let's write this correctly
um
yeah I think we had
PX is equal to MX do plus
QB y but that was in gauge number
one gauge number one means this one over
here in an entirely different gauge
number
two we had
py equal m y dot minus
qbx gauge
two
because the real motion doesn't depend
on the gauge I could use gauge one to
calculate what x does I could use gauge
two to calculate what y does so it's an
odd kind of
logic
um the circular motion about the origin
here corres responded to both P this PX
and this py equal to zero if I set this
equal to zero that's setting myy equal
to
qbx what if I have a circular motion
since after all the magnetic field is
completely uniform one place is exactly
the same as
another I should be able to consider a
circular motion moving around some other
point let's consider that and then
calculate whe whether these quantities
are still
conserved to do that all we have to do
is add an xnot here and a y KN here xot
and Y KN are just the center positions
the central coordinates of the circle
xot and Y KN I've shifted the circle by
amount xot and Y
KN no you're absolutely right it's a
good thing you caught me before I did it
here plus X x +
y doesn't change X do and Y do at
all okay let's calculate what MX do plus
QB
is okay MX
do
is
m
r
Omega minus r Omega sin Omega
t plus QB
Y what is y
r sin Omega t plus y
not
right that's uh that's
PX okay now assuming again that Omega is
related to q and B where is it where's
the connection between here it is QB
over
M then these cancel each
other QB over m is
Omega so these again cancel each other
and we simply find that PX is conserved
it's just equal to y not the central
position of the circular
motion the central position of the
circular motion of course does not
change with time because we're talking
about a circle
moving about a fixed Central
position likewise this py over
here will
be
uh I don't quite have that right do I
it's QB times y
not QB * y not
uh the QB comes from this QB over
here and the py is minus
QB
xnot so you see what the physical
meaning of the momenta is it's something
entirely
unexpected the two momenta in the two
gauges the X component and the Y
component which are conserved quantities
simply correspond to the coordinate
locations of the circle about which the
particle is
revolving and what the conservation
tells you is that the central location
of the circle doesn't move just stays
there entirely unexpected way to think
about momentum
conservation
but this is exactly the way a Charged
particle moves in a magnetic field so
you have to trust lrange and Hamilton
and so forth forth that they knew what
they were doing and you have to trust
Gage in variance but the mathematics
gives you uh gives you the right answer
and in fact gives you the right answer
in probably what's the easiest possible
way just to use the conservation
laws okay let's stop for questions for
the moment
yeah what's
that this one
you mean it's
units
yeah I don't know what's the units of Q
do you know yeah
exactly yeah if you choose consistent
units the units will be
consistent all right
so uh let's go one step further and do
um one other thing let's put back the uh
uh the electric field let's put back the
electric field if I put back the
electric
field
then and let's take this PX over here
let's put um let's put an electric field
in the X Direction all right then it
will not be the case anymore that PX
will be
conserved why if there's an electric
field in the X Direction Let's uh let's
go back let's
okay
um yeah let's put an electric field in
the X direction that means a potential
which looks like Q sorry a potential
which looks
like uh
some electric
field magnitude of the electric field
times
x time minus X I believe if I want the
electric field to point in the X
Direction here e is just the magnitude
of the electric field and remember the
derivative of V subx the derivative of V
with respect to
X is e
subx derivative of V with respect to Y
in this case would be zero so the
derivative of V with respect to to X
would just
be minus sign
here uh would be
E equals zero okay how does that affect
these equations well it doesn't affect
this equation um the the canonical
momentum conjugate to X is still we it
affects this equation here puts in minus
V which is plus e * x q e * X
x q e * X now is the electric field
force or is the electric field energy if
you like now the canonical
momentum in this gauge is still just
piece of X it's just MX do plus QB y it
hasn't changed because this doesn't
depend on the velocity but it's no
longer conserved its time derivative is
equal to the X derivative of this
why that's lres equations lres
equations d by
DT of partial of L with respect to x dot
but that's just p
subx is equal to DL by
DX and now we now we do have an X
dependence we just
have uh QX sorry QE
okay so now instead of having a
conserved quantity we have the new
equation
that let's write it
out the time derivative of PX is MX
dot
plus
QB y
dot I've taken the time derivative of p
subx and that's
equal to Q *
e what about the other equation what
about the equation for p sub y in the
other
gauge that's unchanged because I haven't
put any force in in the y direction so
in the y direction there's been no
change
m y double dot plus or
minus QB
x
dot is still equal to
zero all right now I want to look for a
particular kind of solution of the
equations just for Simplicity only for
Simplicity I want to look for a solution
with no
acceleration let's just look for a
solution with no
acceleration that means the particle is
somehow moving with uniform velocity
ordinary Newton's equations of course
have such Solutions in any velocity is a
possible
velocity well that's not true
anymore let's look for a solution of the
equations with no
acceleration that means that the
velocity has to be constant but it can't
be any constant let's throw these terms
away and see what we get from here we
get that x dot has to be equal to zero
so if we plot X and Y X and Y X dot has
to be equal to zero the particle doesn't
move to the left or the right but from
here we see that y
dot y
dot is equal The Q's cancel let's see y
dot is equal to e over
B is that
right is the ratio of the electric to
the magnetic field
so how does the particle move it moves
with a constant
velocity oh this is constant notice that
y dot is constant and therefore we check
there really is no acceleration I was
correct in looking for a solution with
no acceleration but what I find is a
very special kind of velocity namely a
velocity in the X Direction with uniform
motion equal to the ratio of the
electric to the magnetic field it can be
any anywhere it can move over here it
can move over here but it moves with a
very specific
velocity in the y direction now that's
kind of interesting because I put the
force in in the X
Direction I put the electric field in
the X
Direction e was in this
direction and it causes the particle to
move along the y
direction a bit of a surprise
that's called the hall effect if you
have a magnetic
field if you first of all you have a
magnetic field and no electric field
then first question is there any
solution with no
acceleration Motion in a circle has
acceleration but nevertheless there are
solutions with no acceleration namely a
circle of zero radius where the particle
just sits still that is a solution of
the lorence force
law uh no acceleration no velocity
uh we have no electric field now no
velocity no acceleration that's a
solution but when we turn on the
electric field in the X Direction the
particle moves off along the Y
AIS that's called the hall
effect in fact if you take a
distribution of charge in the plane and
you impose a magnetic field into the
Blackboard and you don't stir up the
particles to give them any special
kinetic energy they will just sit
there but then if you turn on an
electric field in the X Direction the
whole flow of charge will be in along
the Y AIS and the velocity will not
depend on the charge but it will depend
on the ratio of electric to magnetic
field so that's called the hall
effect
and H effect what
and they
toin spin up the
what oh is that
right I don't know about
it I
see it's not in ordinary computers is it
it
is oh okay
why it spins up anything I don't really
know but
uh I can guess why it might but uh let's
not guess okay that's the hall effect
it's very similar and the mathematics is
very close but I won't do it to the
gyroscope effect the gyroscope effect is
if you have a spinning top spinning
along the x-axis and it's in a Gra
gravitational field pulling it down it
doesn't go down it processes in the
perpendicular Direction same
mathematics uh very similar
mathematics okay that's
uh that's the motion of a Charged
particle as
described at least in these three
ways I will write down for you what that
I won't I'll assign it as a
as a problem I think it's one that I did
in class
but to work out the hamiltonian of the
charged
particle and work out Hamilton's
equations and see that you get the same
answers of
course all right so we've been some
through some good stuff electric
particles magnetic particles gauge inv
variants now I want to come to another
form of mechanics
it's really very closely related to
Hamilton's
form it's a kind of abstraction out of
Hamilton's forms and mechanics it's
called a form in terms of pone
brackets now this is highly
abstract it is not something that I
would bother teaching you if it were not
for the fact that it's so centrally
related to Quantum
Mechanics um it is much easier to
understand the quantum mechanical origin
of this than it is to understand the
classical mechanical origin of it one
usually thinks that classical mechanics
is something much easier to understand
than quantum mechanics well at some
point it becomes quite clear that the
classical mechanics is really some um
overly complicated way of
describing uh how the motion of wave
packets behaves in quantum mechanics and
in quantum mechanics the whole idea of
plus home brackets is really very much
easier but nevertheless since we've come
this way without the quantum mechanics
and uh since it is considered a part of
classical mechanics I'm going to teach
you about Pome brackets I think we've
already talked about a little
bit but there's an entirely uh there's a
there's a entire formulation of quantum
mechanic uh classical
mechanics which is based on Bome
brackets Pome brackets and canonical
Transformations we will not get the
canonical Transformations tonight but we
will get the Pome brackets right now
let's begin with Hamilton's equations of
motion now I know I did this before but
never hurts to do a thing again
is it now I always forget where the sign
goes p^2 over 2 m the yeah that's equal
to
Q subi
dot I'm now using p and Q rather than p
and
x and DH by d q sub
I is equal to minus P sub I
dot these are the two Hamilton equations
of motion one for each component I or
rather two for each component
I double as many equations as the lrange
form but the equations of first order
instead of second order they contain
only first time
derivatives all right let's take some
function of p and Q any function uh p^2
+ Q ^2 or any function of momenta and uh
velocities some things that we might
measure um I'm having a hard time
thinking of something that would be
interesting to measure but all the
interesting quantities that one would do
experiments on in a classical mechanical
situation of functions of velocity and
uh and position or equivalently
functions of momentum and velocity and
position so let's take some arbitrary
function
a of all of the PS and all of the
q's all right so here's our phase space
and we have some function which varies
from place to place in the phase space
well- defined
function when the fluid moves through
the phase
space the value of this function changes
with time not because the function
changes with time but because the point
in the fluid is moving through the fluid
and changing with time how does a vary
with time along a
trajectory well that's not too hard to
figure out let's just differentiate it a
DOT this is the time derivative of a
along the
trajectory assuming that a has no
explicit time dependence
well that's going to be the derivative
of a with respect to
p p sub
I time P sub I Dot and when I write a
thing like this you can assume that I
mean sum over
I I'm not going to explicitly write all
the summation signs Plus the derivative
of a with respect to Q
subi time Qi
dot but now let's use use Hamilton's
equations this
becomes partial of a with respect to pie
of
I times looks like there's a minus sign
here I should I want it to start with
the plus sign so let's start with a plus
sign the a by d q
subi and Q subi dot is DH by DP subi
and then we have da by DP
subi times P sub I dot but P sub I DOT
first of all has a minus sign and then
it has
DH by DQ sub
I this combination given two functions
in this case A and
H but they could be any two functions of
positions and
momenta there's an object called the
Pome bracket and this is it so let's
write it
generally for a general pair of
functions let's call them A and B
now then by definition the Pome bracket
of A and B
it's first of all represented by uh by
an A and A B with a common in between
sandwiched between two uh squiggly
brackets like that that's called a Pome
bracket and it's by
definition summation I'll now write the
summation sign just to just when writing
definitions I'll uh just to be uh very
clear summation of
I derivative of a with respect to Q
subi derivative of b b with respect to P
subi minus derivative of a with respect
to P
subi derivative of B with respect to Q
subi the prome bracket of a with B is
not quite the same thing as the prome
bracket of B with
a what's the relationship
not quite this is not
true minus there's a minus sign if I
interchange A and B these two terms in
well if I interchange A and B they
switch and this would be minus so the
Pome bracket is an anti-symmetric
expression involving any two functions
that's number
one so I have to you have to remember
which one you wrote down first have to
keep track of it
but this is it that's its
definition what do we prove a moment ago
we proved that the time derivative
d by DT along a trajectory of any
function of A and P and
Q is equal now it's either plus or minus
um
plus the Pome bracket of a with the
hamiltonian so this of
course includes the two um
the two Hamilton equations for example
supposing we chose for
a what's the simplest thing we could
choose for a either P or Q I'm going to
stop writing sub I let's just do this
for one p and one q but it it's the same
for many of them just uh because I don't
feel like writing subscripts all over
the place let's concentrate on one p
And1 q but nothing I do uh is uh special
to that
case you conf figure figure out where to
put the summation signs and the
indices um what's the simplest thing
that a could
be
P well p is pretty simple what
else anything
simpler how about well Zero's zero is
very simple one is pretty simple just
the function
one the function which is everywhere is
the same on the entire phase space
doesn't vary on the phase space what's
the time time derivative of the function
one as the particle moves through the
face bace zero because one is just one
everywhere let's just check that
supposing I plug in for a I plug in just
one well the derivative of one with
respect to either a p or a q is zero so
quite obviously the Pome bracket of one
with anything is zero okay so the
function one does not change let's let
me make use now of your brilliant
suggestions of a moment ago let's let a
just be p and see what we
get all right the left hand side will
just be DP by
DT the right hand side will be d p by
DQ
DH by
DP
minus DP by
DP DH by
DQ I have just substituted in for
a p DH by
DQ
sorry DP by DQ d h by DP minus DP by DP
d h by DQ now DP by DQ is
zero p and Q are independent variables
and the derivative of one independent
variable with respect to another is just
plain zero so this is
zero what about DP by
DP that's just one and so we find d8 DP
by DT is just DH by DQ one of Hamilton's
equations the other Hamilton equation is
d q by
DT is equal to now we substitute in DQ
by
DQ DH by
DP and now we're going to have another
term where we'll have DQ by DP but
that's zero DQ by DP is zero DQ by DQ is
so the other Hamilton equation is also
of the
form that the time time derivative of an
arbitrary function of p and Q is in fact
equal to the Pome
bracket of the function with the
hamiltonian so we're sort of reducing
now um the physics all of classical
physics to a kind of algebraic structure
involving proone
brackets let me tell you a few
properties that Pome brackets have
they're actually suff efficient to
recover any plusone bracket that you
might be interested
in
uh I'm just going to write down some
properties first of all we've already
encounted one
property a with
B is minus B with a
you can think of this as a kind of um
axiomatization of mechanics based on
Pome
brackets why is it interesting to do so
it isn't until you come to Quantum
Mechanics but it is very very centrally
well it may be interesting but
uh
uh it really achieved its um its full
Glory shall we say when it was realized
that how closely it is connected to the
algebraic structure of quantum mechanics
a with B plus bracket of a with B is
minus the Pome bracket of B with a all
right how about the plusone bracket of p
with
P now we could write I'm going to do p
with P but then I'll tell you what the
answer is if there are any number of
variables what is p with P well that's
equal to partial of p with respect to P
partial of Q with respect to Q sorry
partial of p with respect to
Q partial of Q with respect to
[Music]
p
h yeah you're
right good I don't even need to do
it the Pome bracket of p with p is equal
to minus the prome bracket of p with P
from the above rule here but anything
anything is equal to its own negative Z
so Pome bracket of p with p is equal to
the Pome bracket of Q with
q and is equal to
zero now we can go a little bit
further if we have a system of n
coordinates then we can take the Pome
bracket of one p with another with
another one I with
J we still get zero it's easy to
prove and we'll also get zero for the
q's you can see there's a
symmetry well not an exact symmetry but
some symmetrical relationships between
p's and q's they're on the same
footing uh how about p with q or let's
go to Q with
P plusone bracket of Q with
P that's equal to partial of Q with
respect to Q
partial of p with respect to
P minus partial of Q with respect to P
Q well the derivative of a q with a p or
a P with a Q is zero so this is
zero the derivative of a q with a q or a
P with a p is one and so the Pome
bracket of Q with p is just
one more General
if I have q sub I and P
subj then that's zero if I is not equal
to J for example if we take the Pome
bracket of the x coordinate with the Y
momentum that's zero so this is zero if
I is not equal to J and it's one if I is
equal to
J the symbol for
that is is the chronica Delta symbol i j
Delta i j Delta i j is by
definition Z if I equal
J not equal to J excuse me one if I
equals
J now notice that there is a little
asymmetry Q with p is minus p with Q so
if I were to put p with Q I would get
minus one instead of one so you have to
remember Q if Q is first and P is second
then the com not the commutator the um
the Pome bracket is
one but otherwise there's a great deal
of
symmetry in fact the general structure
of classical mechanics is that whenever
you interchange q and PS there's always
a minus sign
it's called the simplec structure of
classical
mechanics
okay all right some other
rules here's
something how about the Pome bracket of
Q sub I well I'll do it without indices
and then I'll tell you the general
answer the Pome bracket of Q with any
function of Q and
P let's do p p with any function of
qmp taking the plus own bracket of a
function with respect to P does
something to that function let's see
what it does it gives you first of all
DP by
DQ DF by
DP minus the P by
DQ
DF sorry DP by DQ DF by DP
minus right DP by DQ DF by DP that's
right dpdp thank
you DF DF by
DQ now the first term is zero DP by DQ
is zero
second term DP by DP is one and so it
just gives
minus DF by
DQ in other words rule taking the
plusone bracket of an arbitrary function
with respect to P is the same as taking
its derivative with respect to Q with a
minus
sign if we wanted to do this with many
Vari Ables it would be the pon bracket
of a
function with P sub I gives you the
derivative of the function with respect
to Q subi so taking pone brackets with
PS and q's is basically the act of
taking the derivative with respect to p
and Q likewise
is equal to plus DF by DP
subi so taking the Pome bracket with a Q
differentiates with respect to P taking
the Pome bracket with P differentiates
with respect to q but you have to keep
track of the minus
signs
so
um actually I think there's up there's
one
more ingredient that you need to add in
that would allow you to have a full
algebra of Pome
brackets uh that could be used to atise
classical mechanics I don't particularly
like atiz
anything but knowing these rules here is
not quite enough to tell you what the
pon bracket just knowing these rules
without knowing supposing nobody told
you what a Pome bracket was they told
you that Pome brackets satisfy these
relationships
here
H I'll tell you in a minute something
like that
um yeah that that is there is a
linearity yeah I'll write that down in a
minute uh they told you there such
things called Pome brackets they told
you a little bit about the Pome brackets
these things here and then also told you
that
mechanics can be
summarized by saying that
the time derivative of anything is the
Pome bracket of that thing with h how
much do you need to know about Pome
brackets that you could start operating
and completely forget where everything
else came from well you need to know I
think I think whoever said linearity I
think you do need that all right so
here's here's the linearity it hadn't
even occurred to me but yes
A +
[Music]
B all right linearity means the
following it means that if you take any
number times a and take its Pome bracket
with respect to
B it's just the same as multiplying the
Pome bracket by
Alpha so that means if you multipli a by
two it's Pome brackets with everything
would just be twice as is big no
surprise
there another thing if you take the Pome
bracket of a + C with
B that just gives you the Pome
bracket of a with B you can check these
things now check it from the definition
a with B plus the plus bracket of C with
B these two things together are called
linearity
the linearity of the Pome bracket with
respect to one of the
entries if you double it you double a
Pome bracket if you add two things
together and take that Pome bracket with
B it gives you the sum of the two Pome
brackets that's almost
enough to determine the Pome bracket of
anything with anything else any function
of p and Q with any other function of p
and Q There is one more
element what happens if I take a * B
times now not plus a * B with the plus
with with
C well let's work it out and then
abstract from what I work out the the
general answer what is this this is
equal to derivative with respect to Q of
ab times derivative with respect to
P of
C minus the derivative with respect to P
of
ab times the derivative of C with
respect to
q but now all we have to use is the
product rule for
derivatives the product rule for
derivatives says that this is a times
the derivative of B with respect to
Q times the derivative of C with respect
to
P now let me not finish this expression
I'll come back to the other half of it
but let me write it let me combine it
with a times the derivative of B with
respect to P times derivative of C with
respect to
Q that's that's the term that I get when
I do the derivatives by pulling out A
and differentiating B then there's
another term where the derivative hits B
and not a that will be very similar
except A and B will be interchanged so
that would be
B times the derivative of a with respect
to Q derivative of C with respect to
P minus
B derivative of a with respect to P
derivative of C with respect to Q all
right if you summarize it all and put it
all
together this piece here is just a times
the Pome bracket of B with
C A times the deriva times the Pome
bracket of B with c and this one is just
B time the plus bracket of a with c
see all right so the Pome bracket
of ab with
C is a times the personone of B with C
plus b times the proone of a with
C that believe it or not plus knowing
some a few fundamental Pome brackets
between p and Q enables you to calculate
any Pome
bracket that's enough to get started
calculate sums of things P's plus Q's
calculate product and eventually to
calculate any function with any other
function uh I'll let you experiment
around with that and see that uh that
you can calculate or at least any
functions that can be written as sums of
products of functions of p and
Q even infinite sums and products can be
computed so these basic
rules
linearity the product
rule the
anti-symmetry and the fact that Pome
brackets of p with q or zero or one and
so forth those completely
determine the entire family of Pome
brackets of anything with anything else
and if you then add that the rules of
the game are that the time derivative
where did I where did I put it I think I
erased it that the time derivative of
anything is Pome bracket with a
hamiltonian that is another formulation
kind of axiomatic formulation of
classical
mechanics that of course is not
independent of the others it follows
from the others but uh it is another
rather elegant uh the French were great
at this kind of super Elegance it wasn't
the French who invented quantum
mechanics
so uh they were very very good
uh what's
that uh
yeah Oiler was a German Germans were not
as good at its super
Elegance
yeah uh this was before
boraki boraki didn't exist of course
uh this was before bourbaki but there
was no question the French were
extremely good at finding these very
elegant Hamilton was another Frenchman
and uh Newton was another
Frenchman and uh but the people who
really well the person who really uh the
two people who
really put Pon brackets and all this
stuff on the
map were Heisenberg and
D and not in the context of classical
mechanics so this will be next quarter
not this
[Music]
quarter the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu